Guide to the James B. Duke and Lillian McCredy Duke Divorce Records, 1904-1906
Duke University. University Archives
James B. Duke and Lillian McCredy Duke Divorce records 1904-1906
Duke University. University Archives
Duke, Lillian M.
1.5 linear feet Extent: 1200 Items
Lillian McCredy Duke was the first wife of James B. Duke. The two were married in 1904 and divorced in 1906. The papers in this collection are related to the divorce proceedings. The materials in this collection contain correspondence, newspaper clippings, case exhibits, trial transcripts, and envelopes. The material ranges in date from 1904-1906.
UA.01.01.0002
Language: Material in english
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The James B. Duke and Lillian McCredy Duke Divorce Records, 1904-1906 were received by the University Archives as a gift in December 2009.
Biographical Note
Lillian Fletcher McCredy Duke was the first wife of James Buchanan Duke. The two were married in 1904, but shortly divorced in 1906. Before marrying James Duke, Lillian had been married to William F. McCredy. That marriage, too, ended in divorce.
Collection Overview
The Duke Divorce records span the years 1904 to 1906. The two boxes contain correspondence and media regarding the divorce trial between Lillian and James B. Duke and appear to have been part of the evidence submitted at the divorce trial. The bulk of the correspondence is letters from Lillian to both James and her aunt G. E. Townes. There is one letter addressed to Lillian sent by her aunt. The rest of the material includes clippings, exhibits from the trial, trial transcripts, a detective report, and a bill of sale to Lillian's brother John A. Fletcher. The collection is grouped into the following series: Correspondence, Clippings, Court Case Related, Exhibits, and Publications.
Subject Headings
Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; Duke, Lillian McCredy; Duke family
Related Material
James Buchanan Duke Papers, 1777-1990 and undated
Rare Book Manuscript and Special Collections Library at Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1905-1906, (.3 box)
  The Correspondence series is three folders of letters written by Lillian to James Duke and her aunt. The first folder contains the correspondence of Lillian Duke to her aunt. These letters range in date from March 1905 to April 1906 with two undated. The letters cover subjects of money, visiting, thievery, and family affairs. The early letters refer to casual affairs, mostly regarding when she is going to visit her aunt next or the monthly allowance she sends her aunt. Two of the letters, dated March 1906, reflect a heated exchange with her aunt over a supposed theft. Lillian accused her aunt of stealing a wig out of her dresser drawer and closed by threatening the end of their friendship if she did not return it.
  Lillian's husband James is mentioned only briefly in the letters despite their coincidence with her divorce proceedings. However, in her later letters, she refers to her trial and requests the help and council of her aunt.
  Folder two contains one letter, written to Lillian by her aunt in response to the accusation of stealing. In it, she takes great offense at the charge brought upon her. Although undated by the author or recipient, this letter can be dated March 1906 based on the accompanying correspondence of Lillian Duke.
  The last folder of correspondence is filled with letters written by Lillian to her then husband, James B. Duke. They range in date from July, 1905 to September, 1905 and are of a more personal nature. The bulk refers to the loneliness and hardship felt by Lillian while James was overseas in Europe on business. While James was overseas, events unfolded that precipitated him to bring charges of adultery against Lillian and file for divorce. These letters were later admitted as evidence in the trial.
  The last letter is undated, though it was written after she had been served with divorce papers. In this letter, Lillian implores James to hear her side of events and claims that he has only been listening to unreliable sources. She goes on to beg for him to drop the charges of adultery and to take her back.
  - Lillian Duke to Mrs. G. E. Townes (aunt), March, 1905-April, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Lillian to James B. Duke, July, 1905-September, 1905, undated (Box 1)
  - Mrs. G. E. Townes to Lillian Duke, March, 1906 (Box 1)
- Clippings, (.3 box)
  The Clippings series contains newspaper clippings taken from various newspapers and were compiled by a clipping service of Ben B. Hampton and Co., New York. The bulk of the clippings are from May 1906. The clippings include excerpts from the trial proceedings and testimony of one of the chief witnesses, Lillian Duke's former servant Miss Sands.
  - Clippings, Sept., 1905-May, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Loose Clippings, Sept., 1905-Feb., 1906 (Box 1)
- Court Case Related Material, (.3 box)
  The Court Case Related Material series contains a variety of documents from the divorce. First is a detective report from September 1905 commissioned by James B. Duke. There is a detailed ledger for each day of observing Lillian's house and actions. Also included are trial transcripts of testimony given by witnesses. There is a statement by Julia Schaeffer, the cook for Mr. Duke after the divorce proceedings as well as a note from "a woman" who claims Lillian is a liar and calls her out for ruining her previous husband. Other inclusions are a folder of empty envelopes, and a bill of sale to Lillian's brother, John A. Fletcher. The bill of sale documents Lillian selling all her property that remains at the Duke estate to her brother for the sum of one dollar. Items include a Mercedes automobile, two horses, pillows, jewelry, clothing, and other items.
  - September 1905 Detective Report (Box 1)
  - Trial Transcriptions, Mar. 30, 1906-Apr. 18, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Julia Schaeffer Statement, undated (Box 1)
  - Anonymous Note "A Woman," undated (Box 1)
  - Bill of Sale to John A. Fletcher, brother of Lillian Duke, Oct. 28, 1905 (Box 1)
  - Empty Envelopes, June, 1905-February, 1906 (Box 1)
- Exhibits, (.75 box)
  The Exhibit series features fifteen folders of documents used as evidence in the courtroom. Listed on each document is the court date, April 27, 1906. The bulk of the exhibits are European issues of the New York Herald newspaper featuring personal ads that were said to be private messages sent between Lillian Duke and correspondent Major Frank Huntoon. These newspapers date from December 8, 1904, to January 29, 1905. James B. Duke is supposedly referred to as "octopus" in these messages.
  - Exhibit A: Photo of Huntoon, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit B, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit C, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit D, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit E, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit F, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit G, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit H, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit I, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit J, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit K, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit L, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit M, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit N, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit O, Apr. 27, 1906 (Box 2)
- Publications, (.25 box)
  The Publications series contains two issues of the New York Inquirer. One is dated January 26, 1906, and the other is from February 4, 1906. Both issues feature short articles regarding the divorce suit between Lillian Duke and James B. Duke.
  - New York Inquirer, Jan. 26, 1906 (Box 2)
  - New York Inquirer, Feb. 4, 1906 (Box 2)